Daf is נ"ט Net 59. We start a little bit behind on
נ"ח עמוד ב, Naf Ches Amud Beis, five lines before the משנה
Mishnah by the two dots. So we have a little bit of
catching up to do, but let's get started. So רבי יהודה אומר
אם נטלה הנוצה פסולה. Rabbi Yehuda omer im nitlah hanotzah pesulah. So
Rabbi Yehuda said,
this is by things that are not problems but don't make it
a טריפה. treifa. So one is the loss of the wings. Rabbi
Yehuda said if the down is missing it's a טריפה. treifa. And
then we have that whole wonderful story about how
whoever it was did the experiment to refute Rabbi Yehuda. What was
his name again? רבי שמעון בן חלפתא. Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta. Thank
you. פסולה Pesulah here is assumed to
mean טריפה, treifa, right?
פסולה Pesulah here is assumed to mean טריפה. treifa.
Why would you say טריפה? treifa?
I don't know. אמר רבי יוחנן רבי יהודה ורבי ישמעאל אמרו דבר
אחד. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Yishmael amru davar echad. Rabbi
Yochanan said Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Ishmael essentially said the same thing
relating to the down of birds. Rabbi Yehuda הדר אמרן, hadar amran,
which we said that the down is necessary and makes the animal
a
טריפה. treifa. רבי ישמעאל דתנן, Rabbi Yishmael detnan, as we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, רבי ישמעאל אומר הנוצה מצטרפת. Rabbi Yishmael omer hanotzah
mitztarefet. The down combines. Combines for what? רש"י Rashi reads this, which
is not the original source, if you look at the side you
see it's sourced in טהרות. Taharas. רש"י Rashi reads this to be
talking about a פיגול, pigul, that if a כהן kohen is planning
on eating the meat of a bird קרבן korban together with the
down, it's considered like flesh and it's like פיגול. pigul. How do
you eat that like, I don't know. But anyway, that's like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that treats it to some degree like the flesh
in the sense of if it's removed it causes a problem. And
here רש"י Rashi says the point that Seth mentioned at the משנה,
Mishnah, that this would become like the issue of a גלודה gluda
of a skinned cow. So removed נוצה, notzah, the removed down, would
be like the skin. And that's where רש"י Rashi makes the comparison.
If it's being considered to be like the flesh here, so it's,
well, we know the problem that flesh is the same as skin.
Skin is actually you don't have פיגול pigul for skin. But anyway,
it's close enough and that's a similar position about why it would
be then considered like the animal has a removed skin by a
cow, removed down here. תוספות Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says what are
you talking about, this משנה Mishnah comes from a discussion of טהרות
Taharas and it comes from a discussion about how much is a
minimum size of a food matter to make it be able to
become טמא. tamei. You need the size of a כביצה. k'beitzah. And
what happens if you have the meat of a bird but it's
not a full כביצה, k'beitzah, but you also have some of the
down? Now here you don't have to say that the down is
edible like רש"י Rashi at all because one of the principles of
what you can do to get a minimum size of something that
can make it טמא tamei is not only food but something that
is a שומר shomer for the food, something that protects the food
like for example a shell around a nut. So here רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael is saying oh the down counts because that is a
protection of the actual flesh. And there the comparison to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda makes a lot more sense. We're not calling it flesh
but we're saying the down does a necessary job of protecting the
flesh.
If you had just down would it also be?
No, it has to be protecting the actual thing. It combines with
the meat but it doesn't count on its own. It needs a
majority meat?
Probably, I don't know. I'd have to check. Okay, okay, הנוצה מצטרפת.
Hanotzah mitztarefet. אמר רבא דילמא לא, Amar Rava dilma lo,
maybe it's not the same. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהודה הכא
אלא לעניין טריפה. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda hacha ela l'inyan
treifa. Maybe Rabbi Yehuda only says his position by טריפה treifa דליכא
מידי דמגין עלה, d'leika midi d'magein alah,
that without the down nothing is protecting it. אבל לעניין פיגולי כרבנן
סבירא ליה. Aval l'inyan pigulei k'rabbanan sevira leh.
Now this is רש"י's Rashi version. When it comes to פיגול pigul
maybe he'll be like the rabbis that it's not considered a meat.
It protects but it's not meat. That's רש"י's Rashi version that the
discussion here is פיגול. pigul. Let's just finish it and then I'll
tell you תוספות's Tosafot version. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי ישמעאל התם
אלא לעניין פיגולי. V'ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yishmael hatam ela l'inyan
pigulei. Rabbi Ishmael only says his position when it comes to פיגול
pigul that it's considered like meat meaning it's edible. אבל לעניין טריפה,
Aval l'inyan treifa, when it comes to טריפה, treifa, maybe he would
say אגוני לא מגני, agonei lo magnei, it does not protect. So
the issue according to רש"י Rashi is a clear basis of distinguishing.
Is it like meat is one question, does it protect is a
different question and you can't compare the two. How about תוספות Tosafot
where the whole point was that it was considered to be like
a שומר? shomer? So that does seem like a stronger comparison. So
תוספות Tosafot says the answer is wait a minute,
oh, right,
so תוספות Tosafot says by שומר shomer the expression of שומר shomer
is not the question of whether it protected the animal when the
animal was alive, right? The issue of שומר shomer is that whether
it's doing that function now that it's serving as food. And that's
the distinction of the גמרא. Gemara. רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position about
טריפה treifa is saying that the down is needed to protect the
animal when it's alive and to keep it alive. To say it's
a שומר shomer for food and for laws of טומאה tumah says
right now you want the down around the meat to help keep
the meat clean and to help preserve the meat. So the גמרא
Gemara says they're not necessarily the same. What serves to protect the
animal when it's alive is not necessarily what serves as a שומר
shomer for the meat now that the animal is dead. Did they
take out the word
פיגול pigul then?
Well, he takes out the word פיגול. pigul. I mean רש"י Rashi
actually says if you look at רש"י, Rashi, the first wide line
רש"י, Rashi, פיגולי גרסינן. pigulei garsinan. Whenever רש"י Rashi says גרסינן garsinan
it means that there was either a different version around or it
actually means that not only was there a different version and רש"י
Rashi is affirming his version, sometimes it means רש"י Rashi changed the
version to make it
consistent.
I don't know, תוספות Tosafot doesn't tell you exactly what his text
was, but it's clear רש״י Rashi had to do something with the
text to make it work according to him. Okay, so that's the
issue of the דם. dam. Now we move on to the next
משנה. mishna. One last משנה, mishna, this is it! We did טרפות
trefas of בהמה, behemas, problems which aren't טרפות, trefas, טרפות trefas of
birds, things which are problems which aren't טרפות. trefas. And the last
משנה mishna makes a point that I've been making from the beginning,
that טרפה treifa does not mean the animal is going to die,
not alone, because an animal could die for other reasons: old age,
an illness. טרפה treifa specifically has to do with a fatal type
of a wounding, and that's the point this last משנה mishna makes.
So let's take a look. אחוזת הדם, achuzas ha-dam, an animal that
has a blood clot, והמיושנת, ve-ha-me-ushenes,
or that it
inhaled smoke, smoke inhalation, והמצוננת, ve-ha-metzunenah, or it has chills, a frostbite
maybe, ושאכלה
הרדופני, ve-she-achlah hordufni, ate some type of a spice or which burns
a hole in its insides, we'll see about that in the גמרא,
Gemara, ושאכלה צואת תרנגולים, ve-she-achlah tzoas tarnegolim, or ate from the dung
of chickens, which was presumably a concern about you know maybe the
bacteria, whatever, anyway the parasites they were
concerned
for. גמרא Gemara will discuss that.
או ששתתה מים הרעים, o she-shasas mayim hara'im, or bad water. So
all these things actually we can understand, you know, how they observed
them and they saw that this sometimes led to death. They didn't
have a whole theory of germs out there, they more thought about
poisons, but a lot of these things is very clear. Anyway, so
all these things which will be fatal, but they were not injuries.
So in those types of cases, כשרה, kesherah, it is not a
טרפה. treifa.
And then it says, אבל אכלה סם המות, aval achlah sam ha-maves,
if they poisoned, או שהכישה נחש, o she-hikish nachash, or it was
bit by a snake, so you have a real poison issue. In
those cases, מותרת משום טרפה, muteres mishum treifa, it's okay because of
טרפה, treifa, again it's not an injury, a wound, ואסורה משום סכנת
נפשות, ve-asurah mishum sakanas nefashos, but don't eat it because if it's
imbibed poison, ingested poison, then you'll get that poison, so obviously to
protect your own life you shouldn't eat it, it's a health risk,
but technically it's not טרפה. treifa. So we won't give you lashes
if you eat it, but you are putting your own life at
risk and it's forbidden to eat because of the health risk. Now
what I think is interesting is that the earlier cases about the
bad water and these other things, it did not think was poison,
right? It thinks that you could eat those things, which could make
the animal sick and make the animal die, but it won't hurt
you.
What is bad water?
Bad water, you know, like I don't know it's left out, it's
stale, it's been...
Yeah, but if it's left out then it's because of the snake,
in which case it's...
That is my point. My point there is that the גמרא, Gemara,
not the גמרא, Gemara, the משנה mishna is always concerned about exposed
water and concerned because of snakes, which is a concern about poison.
And here you have something which acknowledges that actually water that is
somehow soiled,
bacteria-filled, they didn't know about bacteria but whatever, could cause, you know,
could cause illness and death to the animal, but implicitly it isn't
poison, right? So I think that's quite interesting if you hold that
side by side with the whole assumptions about the exposed liquids, which
is always a concern about poison. So anyway,
maybe it felt that if it was being eaten by the animal,
the animal would process the poison, so it would not be fatal
to humans unless it was directly ingesting poison and then there was
a concern that it would remain fatal, it would get in the
meat and remain fatal to humans. Okay, so let's see the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss a
little bit about some of these specifics about these fatal things. היליתה
חילתית טרפה, hilitah chilsis treifa, if it swallowed חילתית, chilsis, which is
a type of, I forget what the English says it as, coland,
I don't know, Joe, what do you got for the English there
for חילתית? chilsis? Oxford doesn't transcribe...
Oh, Alyester I think it was or
something,
hold on... No, asafoetida. That's a spice. Okay. Anyway the גמרא Gemara
understood that this was an extremely sharp spice which would burn a
hole in the inner organs of an animal if it ate it.
So that would be now interesting, particularly the esophagus, right? What? Well,
yeah, but so the interesting thing is, so it's a טרפה, treifa,
meaning his point is this does not just make it a fatal
disease, this actually makes it a טרפה, treifa, because this will actually
burn a hole, and that's getting back to the טרפה treifa issue
about some type of a wound or an injury. So for this
spice, then it's a טרפה. treifa.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? דמינקבו להו למעיה. de-minkevu lehu lemayeha. It makes
a hole in its inner organs. מתיב רב שיזבי, masive Rav Shizbi,
so רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi asked on this, we have a ברייתא
Beraita which elaborates on our משנה. mishna. אחוזת הדם והמיושנת ושאכלה הרדופני
ושאכלה צואת תרנגולים ושתתה מים הרעים, achuzas ha-dam ve-ha-me-ushenes ve-she-achlah hordufni ve-she-achlah
tzoas tarnegolim ve-shasas mayim hara'im, okay so far everything in our list,
eating these things which'll cause it to die, והמיושנת, ve-ha-me-ushenes, or inhaled
smoke, I'm sorry, skip the line.
והיליתה טיעא חילתית ופלפלין, ve-hilitah ti'ah chilsis ve-pilpelin, or if it swallowed
טיעא, ti'ah, which is some other type of bad herb, and חילתית
chilsis which was mentioned and... peppers, presumably hot peppers. או סם המות,
O sam hamavet, or if it ate poison, in any of these
cases, כשרה. kesherah. It's kosher. Yes, it might cause it to die,
but it remains a כשרה. kesherah. So the question is going to
be it says חלתית chiltit and it's not a טרפה. treifah. Right?
Yes, it's fatal, but it doesn't make a hole. It's not a
טרפה. treifah. הקישה נחש או שנשכה כלב שוטה, Hekishah nachash o shenashchah
kelev shotah, if it was bitten by a snake or by a
mad dog, מותרת משום טרפה ואסורה משום סכנת נפשות. muteret mishum treifah
ve'asurah mishum sakanat nefashot. It's not a טרפה, treifah, but yeah, we're
going to get to that, but it is a problem about a
health risk,
rabies presumably. And now, if you eat from meat that was bit
by a rabid dog, will that transfer rabies to you? Does anybody
know?
I was wondering that.
Do you know? Yeah. If it's not adequately cooked, it could. You
have to cook it enough to kill the virus.
So this adds the poison.
This
adds, so the גמרא's Gemara going to ask about the poison, but
let's, so the גמרא's Gemara going to say קשיא חלתית אחלתית. Kashya
chiltit achiltit. First we have a contradiction to שמואל Shmuel because it
says here that if it eats חלתית, chiltit, it's not a טרפה,
treifah, and שמואל Shmuel says it is a טרפה, treifah, it burns
a hole. קשיא סם המות אסם המות, Kashya sam hamavet asam hamavet,
and the poison, right? Our משנה mishnah says very reasonably that poison
is a health risk when an animal swallows it and this ברייתא
baraita said it was not. So here let's see what the answers
are. חלתית אחלתית לא קשיא, Chiltit achiltit lo kashya, the חלתית chiltit
is not a contradiction. כאן בעלין כאן בקרטין. Kan be'alin kan bekartin.
It's a difference between the leaves and the seeds. Okay, the leaves
are bad and might be fatal but won't burn a hole, but
the seeds are really, burn a hole. If anybody ever handled like,
you know, hot peppers, chili peppers, right, there's a huge difference between
when you eat the skin of the chili pepper, which is a
little sharp or whatever, and the seed, which ממש mamash you get
a little on your, you know, on your lip or something and
it burns for hours. So anyway, so there's a difference between the
leaves and the seeds. The seeds will actually make it a טרפה.
treifah. Okay. סם המות אסם המות לא קשיא, Sam hamavet asam hamavet
lo kashya, the issue of poison is not the contradiction. הא דידה
הא דאדם. Ha deidah ha de'adam. Did it eat human poison or
animal poison? Some things are poisonous for animals but not for humans.
So if it ate something that is only poisonous for animals, then
the animal is not a טרפה treifah and you can even eat
it. But if it ate something that is a poison for a
human, then the animal might not be a טרפה treifah but you
can't eat it. So either way, it's not טרפה. treifah. It's not,
right, the point of these משנה mishnah and ברייתא baraita is not
a טרפה, treifah, but some types of poisons are poisonous for animals,
not for humans in terms of the health risk, and this חלתית
chiltit if it's the seeds does make it a טרפה. treifah. Okay.
סם המות דבהמה היינו הרדופני. Sam hamavet debehemah hainu herdufni. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, if it's just poisonous for animals, then
it already mentioned הרדופני, herdufni, which is some type of again, some
type of a plant which is considered to be poisonous or fatal
for animals. So the גמרא Gemara says תרי גווני סם המות. Trei
gavnei sam hamavet. All right, there's different types of poison. There's the
הרדופני herdufni and there's other types of things that are poisonous for
animals and they were all being mentioned. Okay. מאי טיאה, Mai tea,
what is this טיאה tea which is also considered something that will
cause the animal to die?
So אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, עיקרא דמרירתא. ikra demarirta. It
is the root of מרירתא, marirta, some say מרידתא. maridta. So מרירתא
marirta might imply some type of a, you know, of a bitter
herb. רש"י Rashi says שורש של תורה, shoresh shel torah, I have
no idea what תורה torah is. What do they say here? What
does the ArtScroll say for the English? I looked all these things
up beforehand, not that I can remember. Succory. Okay, who knows? What
does the ArtScroll say? Does it refuse to translate? Okay, fine. אמר
רב
יהודה. Amar Rav Yehudah. So I'm taking the approach of the ArtScroll.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehudah, האי מאן דאכל תלתא תקלי חלתית.
hai man de'achal tlata taklei chiltit. Now we're, if somebody ate, תלתא
תקלי חלתית, tlata taklei chiltit, we're going back to this חלתית, chiltit,
this type of thing which burns a hole in the
intestines, the seeds of it anyway. If you ate three תקלי, tiklei,
which is measures, or a certain type of a measure, three measures
of this חלתית, chiltit, אליבא ריקניא, aliba reikanya, you a human ate
them with an empty heart, empty, well, literally empty heart, but presumably
means an empty stomach. Okay, רש"י Rashi says קודם אכילה, kodem achilah,
you ate them before you know, before you've eaten that morning. משתלח
משכיה, mishtalach mashchei, it'll be so terrible that it'll cause your skin
to fall off. Now אמר רב אבהו, amar Rav Avahu, that you
might think that's an exaggeration, but the גמרא Gemara did believe that
it burns holes in your inner organs. So אמר רב אבהו, amar
Rav Avahu, ובדידי הוה עובדא, uvedidi havah uvda, this happened to me,
ואכלי חד תקלא דחלתית, ve'achli chad takla dechiltit, I only ate one
measure of this חלתית, chiltit, presumably on an empty stomach, ואלו דלא
יתבי במיא, ve'ilu dela yatbi bemaya, and if I'd not jumped in
the water right after I ate it, משתלח משכאי, mishtalach mashchai, my
skin would have come off, fallen off. וקיימתי בעצמי, Vekiyamti be'atzmi, and
I fulfilled in myself the verse החכמה תחיה בעליה, hachochmah techayeh be'aleha,
the wisdom will keep its master alive. So I was, yeah, I
wasn't smart enough not to eat it, but I was smart enough
to jump in the water afterwards. Okay. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, so said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, האי מאן דאכל שיתסר ביעי,
hai man de'achal shitsar beyei, if someone eats sixteen eggs, וארבעין
גוזי, ve'arba'in guzei, and forty nuts, ושבע בותיתא דפרחי, vesheva butita defarchi,
and seven, I have no idea, some type of a seed here
again, some type of a maybe a sunflower seed or whatever. Charlie,
do we know what seed it is? What does ArtScroll say?
Translated caper berry.
Caper berry, what's that? I have no idea.
Why not caper? Why not caper?
Oh, like capers? Okay. Caper berry seeds. Okay,
ושתי רביעתא דדובשא, veshati revi'ta deduvsha, and he drank a רביעית, revi'it,
like three ounces of honey,
all in one meal.
בתקופת, bitkufas, all one meal, בתקופת תמוז bitkufas Tamuz in the summer,
אליבא ריקנא al liba reikana on an empty stomach, ואיעקר v'itakar then
you become sterile. Exactly. So since we're talking in the משנה Mishna
about health risks and we're talking about this כסיסא, chasis, so we're
talking about other things to look out for. Okay. תניא, Tanya, I'm
sorry, excuse me, I didn't read the whole thing. מיטקר תייה דליבא,
mitakar taya d'liba, the your the membranes, the sinews around your heart,
those become uprooted. Your heart somehow becomes dislodged. Not clear whether it
causes you to die or maybe just has you causes you to
have a you know a congestion or a heart attack. Okay. ההוא
בר טביא, Hahu bar tavia, now there was a certain a deer,
son of a deer literally, דאתא לבי ריש גלותא, d'ata l'vei Reish
Galusa, they were brought it to the house of the ריש גלותא
Reish Galusa which was the secular Jewish head of, you know, in
בבל, Bavel, the political head of בבל, Bavel, בצומת הגידין, b'tzomas hagidin,
and I'm sorry, I keep on skipping lines, דהוה נפסק כרעיה בתרייתא,
d'hava nifsak karaia basraisa, that its rear legs were cut, were broken
or cut. You remember what we said, what?
Not amputated though?
Not clear, not clear whether they were completely cut off, not the
whole legs anyway. Some part of the leg, it seems like it
cannot be the whole leg or even high up because again this
is going to be the issue of the צומת הגידין, tzomas hagidin,
which is right by the lowest knee. Okay, but somewhere there was
a it was broken or cut. I'm sorry, what?
Why is this here?
We will see. Let's look at the end of the story. Okay.
בדק רב
בצומת הגידין ואכשריה, Badak Rav b'tzomas hagidin v'achshariya, so רב Rav checked
the צומת הגידין, tzomas hagidin, the collection of sinews right by that
lowest knee and said, oh, it's still there and it's not completely
cut and it's cut presumably below that area, so it's okay. Fine.
So that's things we saw before about the broken rear leg and
the צומת הגידין. tzomas hagidin. סבר למיכל מיניה באומצא. Savar l'meichal minei
b'umtza. He said, oh great, now I'm going to let me go
have some אומצא. umtza. Now אומצא umtza means meat completely raw or
to me like just very quickly, you know, roasted without like a
seriously cooked. How did you say that
part of me then?
That was yeah,
I forget.
Okay, anyway, באומצא, b'umtza, so he wanted to say have a have
a bite of the meat. No questions are being raised here about
נוגע בדבר. nogaya b'davar.
I guess maybe that's a good thing, if you פסקן pasken on
it and then you eat from it, it shows you really think
it's כשר. kosher. We actually had cases like that before.
We had it when your student came, he said they make him,
exactly, exactly.
אמר ליה שמואל, Amar lei Shmuel, so now we'll see why this
is being brought in. שמואל Shmuel said to רב, Rav, לא חייש
מר לנשיכותא, lo chaish mar l'neshichusa, aren't you concerned about snakebite? Meaning
presumably whatever problem it was, it wasn't that the leg was cut
off. There was some cut in the leg area and he said
maybe that cut was a result of the biting of a snake
or some other type of an animal and maybe poison was injected
into it.
Okay, so, so now it's actually interesting right, it's not the דרוסה.
drusa. דרוסה Drusa is when there's clawing with presumed poison and that
makes it a טרפה. treifa. Here it's just a snake biting, but
at least okay, it's not a problem of טרפה. treifa. The things
weren't cut, but how about the concern of poison? אמר ליה מאי
תקנתא? Amar lei mai takansa? So he said back to שמואל, Shmuel,
so what should I do to be safe? So he said נספיה
בתנורא. naspeiya b'sanura. He says put it in an oven. Don't just
do a quick roasting. Cook it for seriously in an oven. דאיהו
בדיק נפשיה, d'ihu badik nafshiya, it will test itself. Based on what
happens in the oven you'll see what will happen if there's poison.
Now you might think it means that the poison will be, you
know, will be like sort of neutralized. But no, let's see what
happens. נספיה, Naspeiya, he put it in the oven. נפל תילחי תילחי.
nafal tilchi tilchi. So it sort of fell to pieces. So it
showed that there was poison in it but somehow that was, that,
you know, that that had the effect once it was cooked. So
he protects so he saved himself from eating it. קרי שמואל עליה
דרב, Kari Shmuel alei d'Rav, so שמואל Shmuel said about רב, Rav,
לא יאונה לצדיק כל און, lo ye'uneh l'tzaddik kol aven, so there
will not come to a righteous person any any, you know,
tragedy, anything bad. So you know because I happened to be there
right when he was about to eat it and I gave him
this warning and it was מן השמים min hashamayim that he was
protected.
קרי רב עליה דשמואל, Kari Rav alei d'Shmuel, so רב Rav had
to return the compliment so he said about שמואל, Shmuel, כל רז
לא אנס לך, kol raz lo anis lach, anything hidden is not
is not you know any secret is not hidden from you. That
שמואל, Shmuel, you're so wise, you thought a about the possibility about
the poison and you also knew how to do something to test
for it. So here is again the theme of not eating meat
that might have poison in it and protecting yourself.
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel were colleagues, right? Yes. So he's calling
him מר? Mar? Yeah,
well yeah. Do they usually do that?
Yeah, מר Mar is actually if you look at some of the
have the גרסא gursa of אבא, Abba, which gets to the question
whether אבא Abba was his proper name or whether אבא Abba was
a word of respect, but מר Mar actually is the word for
a colleague. Okay, and yes please?
Like
they're not concerned with the puncture?
Right, because that's what that's what I was saying that for whatever
reason the concern of a puncture that transfers poison as a type
of a טרפה treifa was limited to דרוסה, drusa, which was clawing.
So very specifically if it's by teeth for whatever reason that's not
in the category of דרוסה. drusa.
So the injection, you were talking about like injections of steroids, that
would fall into the clawing category in terms of a puncture.
Well any puncture, whatever the cause of a puncture is, if... If
the puncture punctures an inner organ, so it's in that first list
of טריפות, treifas, it's a טריפה treifa problem. The issue about the
דרוסה drusa was that it tore the outer skin, but it did
not tear an inner organ. And then we're concerned that somehow the
combination of the clawing with a poison when it doesn't tear an
inner organ. If it's a biting which transfers poison, which is this
case, then ironically
it's not טריפה, treifa, it's not in the דרוסה drusa category and
at most it's the health risk. And that's this case. Okay, so
with this we end up טריפות. treifas. We did animals, we did
birds, and we did things which are טריפות, treifas,
things which are problems, not טריפות. treifas. And the last משנה mishna
summing up that it's not just if it's going to die and
have some fatal problem, that doesn't enough to make it a טריפה.
treifa. Might be a health risk because טריפה treifa is based on
torn.
No no, we're talking about the דרוסה drusa with the puncture versus
the biting
because the real question is why is דרוסה drusa a problem? If
it's not the tearing of the organ, poison is not enough and
the tearing wasn't enough of the outer skin, what's the combination of
the tearing with the poison? And why is it different than the
case of the bite? I really don't know other than that the
point that the רמבּ"ם Rambam makes, which is is that דרוסה drusa
is really the paradigm טריפה treifa of the תורה. Torah. When the
תורה Torah says בשר בּשדה טריפה, basar basadeh treifa, torn, it means
torn by like, you know, clawed at by another animal. So somehow
that gave it a status of being a טריפה, treifa, you know,
in itself. It seems to be. Okay, now we move on, so
now we're done with טריפות. treifas. Now we move on to a
משנה mishna that might have been something that came before טריפות treifas
because before you get to worry about, maybe even before שחיטה, shechita,
before you get to worry about שחטינג shechting it and looking at
the inner organs, you want to make sure you're שחטינג shechting the
right animal, whether the animal's a כשר kosher species of animal. So
anyway, so this for whatever reason comes at the end of all
that discussion because it is more theoretical. Like let's face it, they
knew the basic things they were eating, you know sheep and goats
and cows and ducks and whatever and chickens etc. So after we
have all of this very practical, now we're going to take a
step back and talk anyway about the סימנים simanim of כשר kosher
and non-כשר kosher animals. So let's take a look. סימני בּהמה וחיה
נאמרו מן התורה. Simani behema vechaya ne'emru min hatorah. The indicators, the
characteristics of mammals, חיה chaya and בּהמה, behema, wild, domesticated and undomesticated
animals are given in the תורה, Torah, right? Split hooves and chew
their cud. וסימני העוף לא נאמרו בּתורה. Vesimani ha'of lo ne'emru batorah.
And the תורה Torah did not give any characteristics to identify כשר
kosher birds, it just listed the non-כשר kosher birds, which is a
big problem because since we don't know the identity of the non-כשר
kosher birds and we don't know specific characteristics for כשר kosher birds,
it's hard to know about whether we can eat a certain type
of a bird if we don't have a tradition that it's כשר,
kosher, and we'll get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. So therefore,
but even though the תורה Torah did not give it, here are
some indicators, says the משנה. mishna. כּל שיש לו אצבּע יתירה, Kol
sheyesh lo etzba yeteira, if it has an extra finger.
Did I skip a line? Oh I keep on skipping lines. I'm
sorry. Alright, alright. אבל אמרו חכמים, Aval amru chachamim, but the sages
say, כּל עוף הדורס טמא. kol of hadores tamei. Any predatory bird
is טמא. tamei. Now what exactly does דורס dores mean is not
so clear. Some say it means it swoops down and grabs its
prey, some say it means it holds its prey with one hand
as it sort of eats from it and tears from it with
the other hand. There are different questions of exactly, I mean we
all know in general what it means. It means a, what's that,
what's it called, is
it called predatory?
Birds of prey, yeah. Anyway, so we know in general. But even
within that there are questions of precisely how to define it because,
right, because you want exactly know the line between כשר kosher and
non-כשר. kosher. By the way, the book שיחות חולין Sichos Chullin was
very helpful here.
I'm going to show you pictures in a minute. Oh the page
before the one I xeroxed has three, can you hand me that
Rifka, the, no no, that top one over there, there you go.
He gave three interpretations of what a bird of prey means in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. I'll just read them to you.
So while you're doing that,
and I'll be there in one second.
In terms of, here,
here, here's the plant that causes the berries. Okay anyway,
yeah, so, okay. The birds of prey, what?
Exactly the plants, right?
סימני
בּהמה.
Simani behema.
Right,
הערה ha'ara twenty.
Where was the הערה ha'ara twenty? Go back. And
רש"י. Rashi. Alright, go ahead, what's your question?
So I wanted to get back to understand something about the lungs,
you know גלאט glatt and not. Yep. You said it's how smooth
it is, but what, what would be the line? Like גלאט. glatt.
What?
I don't know, we'll have to bring, yeah, well I'm not surprised,
we'll have to bring somebody in to talk about it. Okay, very
quickly here.
Where were we? Ah, okay.
So רש"י Rashi says that, that birds of prey means it holds
with its claws and picks up from the ground what it eats.
Okay. Wait, picks it up with its beak or with its claws?
I mean like it swoops down and grabs its prey.
Chicken may do that.
Some say chicken, no no, I think it means also that, chickens
peck. Swoops down and claws its prey, yeah.
Domestic chickens don't even fly.
Parrots will peck.
Hey, one says that it holds its prey, it holds its prey
from moving while it claws from its other hand.
One minute.
But
I mean it could be,
one is that, right, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that it eats
it while it's still alive.
All right, I don't have the time to go through all of
it. But anyway, if these three explanations he gives right here is
either it swoops down and grabs its prey, it holds its prey
and claws at it while it's sort of living and thrashing, it's
holding it, and the other is that it eats from its prey
while it's still alive.
So three definitions. What about if it doesn't prey? What if it
doesn't have prey?
Right, if it just eats vegetables like grain, like right, so clear,
but the question is even if it eats, it's not carnivorous is
the point. The definition of bird of prey here is not carnivorous.
There's some sense of being a, you know, attacking. Okay, so how
do you exactly define? Right, notice by the way the word דורס
dores was the same word we used by the דריסה, drisa, by
the clawing, which was the category of טרפה. treifa. Okay, so some
bird of prey, but there's some question of the exact parameters. Yes,
Charlie. Okay. So that, that is a טמא. tamei. כל שיש בו
אצבע יתירה וזפק וקורקבנו נקלף טהור. Kol sheyesh bo etzba yeteira vezeffek
vekorkavano niklaf tahor. Now that, now he's describing both what's not kosher
and what is kosher. Here's how you know something that is kosher,
that it has an extra finger. What does extra finger mean? They
have a very nice picture here. There's a, right,
it
probably means the thing that
looks like the thumb, which is the back finger.
Although some say, that's what רש"י Rashi says. Here I say they
have a very nice picture here. An extra, like on the back
there, yeah. So here you've got your chicken. This little thing which
looks like a half thumb. You see this thing here that looks
like a half thumb? That's what רש"י Rashi says. Some say it
means this very long finger in the middle. Okay, so somehow that's
considered extra.
Maybe because it's longer, longer or
different, it's coming,
it's opposable, either longer, it's extra because it's this long one that's
out of order or because it's opposable and it's more like a
thumb. Okay, וזפק, vezeffek, and it has a crop, וקורקבנו נקלף, vekorkavano
niklaf, and its gizzard can be peeled. Apparently you can peel off
the outer layer of the gizzard. So those are three סימנים simanim
that determine a kosher bird. So the question is, is that enough?
Is it enough that it has those סימנים? simanim? Is it enough
that it's not a bird of prey? You know, or is that
sufficient to determine a kosher bird or not? We'll discuss that when
we get to the גמרא. Gemara. The whole question is something like
turkey and other birds that we don't have a tradition for, are
they kosher? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says: רבי אליעזר בן
צדוק אומר כל עוף החולק את רגליו טמא. Rabbi Eliezer ben Tzadok
omer kol of haholek et raglav tamei. Again, focusing not on defining
what's kosher but what's not kosher. If a bird splits its fingers,
apparently birds of prey, they have two fingers in front and two
in the back. Apparently that also helps them grab their prey. Okay,
so that is not kosher. And
so that is a characteristic of a non-kosher bird.
Also over here you're seeing all these are like the same plane.
Yeah, basically, right. Okay. So, ובחגבים, Uvachagavim, now how about, how about
the grasshoppers? כל שיש לו ארבע רגלים, Kol sheyesh lo arba raglayim,
if it has four legs, main legs, וארבע כנפים, vearba knafayim, four
wings, these are what make it kosher. וכרצולאים וכרצולאים, Vechartzula'im vechartzula'im,
and it has jumper legs. Do you basically have a picture? It
has six, but there
are
four normal feet or the big ones here, you see these huge
ones, these are the jumper legs.
If you don't see them then your fingers just block.
It has two jumper legs. וכנפיו חופין את רובו, Veknafav hofin et
rubo, and its wings cover the majority of the length of the
body. That defines it as a grasshopper. רבי יוסי אומר ושמו חגב.
Rabbi Yossi omer ushmo chagav. Now once again you get to something
that is very observable to something that requires a tradition that makes
it a lot harder. It has to be called a חגב. chagav.
It's not enough that it has those things, it has to be
in the category of things called a חגב, chagav, which is great.
So then what is it? So that you would only know if
you had a tradition.
Does that rely on someone else's tradition?
Maybe. ובדגים, Uvidagim, and by fish, כל שיש לו סנפיר וקשקשת, kol
sheyesh lo snapir vekaskeset, by fish anything that has a fins and
scales. רבי יהודה אומר שני קשקשין וסנפיר אחד. Rabbi Yehuda omer shetei
kaskasin vesnapir echad. It has to have two scales because קשקשין kaskasin
are in plural and it's enough to have one fin. I don't
know what type of animal only has two scales and one fin.
Is there even one normal?
Not clear. ואלו הן הקשקשין, Ve'eilu hen hakaskasin, these are what the
scales are. הקבועין בו, Hakvuim bo, that are affixed to it and
presumably staying in their place. So those are the, meaning that's the
scales. וסנפירין, Vesnapirin, and the fins, הפורח בהן, haporei'ach bahen, those are
the things that it uses to swim with. So just to describe
that it means fins and scales.
He is giving the minimum.
He is saying the minimum,
like two and one.
Two and one, that is what he is saying, at least. Right.
Michael was asking whether the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say one
and one or would the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say two and
two? Yeah, we don't know. Okay, let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. So this is it, these are all the סימנים.
simanim. Did they ever find a
fish like that? Yeah. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so our Rabbis taught:
אלו הן סימני.
Eilu hen simanei. כל בהמה שמעלה גרה, Kol behemah shema'alah gerah,
if any animal chews its
cud, בידוע שאין לה שיניים למעלה, beyadu'a she'ein lah shinayim lema'lah, you'll
know that it has
no upper teeth, apparently a cow, here's a nice little picture, look
at a cow, right, so you see this picture? It has bottom
teeth but no upper teeth.
Oh, it has upper molars.
Right, but not like no front teeth, what שיניים shinayim here we're
talking about front teeth. Okay, no upper front teeth,
okay, וטהורה, vetehorah, and it's kosher. Now that of course is what,
it's kosher? Then why do you need the whole thing about split
hooves? And we know it's not true, there are animals that chew
their cuds that don't have split hooves. The Torah has a whole
list of animals that chew their cuds. So we're going to get
to that in a minute. But right now the claim is that
if it has split hooves, then if it chews its cud, then
it doesn't have teeth and it's also kosher. So let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says. וכללא הוא, Vekhlala hu, is
that really a general rule? והרי גמל, Vaharei gamal, how about your
camel? דמעלה גרה הוא, demaleh gerah hu, it chews its cud, ואין
לו שיניים למעלה, ve'ein lo shinayim lema'lah, and it doesn't have, you
know, teeth. So that satisfies your claim about the teeth. וטמא, Vetamei,
it's not kosher, meaning any animal that chews its cud with split
hooves is not kosher. What type of statement was that? So the
גמרא, Gemara, what,
this camel has teeth?
We're going to get to that. It doesn't have like a lot
of teeth but it has two incisors. We'll get to, the גמרא
Gemara is getting there. Okay. So the, so the גמרא Gemara says,
so rather than, so, so how do you deal with that? It
doesn't have teeth but it is טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, גמל ניבי אית ליה, Gamal nivi it leh, it does
have teeth, that and that's why it's טמא. tamei. So now what
we're doing is, and that here if you see these pictures, it
does have what are these called? Are these called incisors? Like these
big, you know, you know like certain animals have like these big
two teeth come out right, are those incisors? Canines too, whatever. רש"י
Rashi says also horses have them apparently. That's what רש"י Rashi says.
Horses do have front upper teeth.
Yeah, but not just upper teeth, meaning these big long two, one
long tooth on each side. Fangs, fangs, whatever, right. Okay. Anyway, do
they Charlie?
I don't know dentistry.
Okay, fine. So what good are you? Okay.
Anyway, dogs have them.
Right. Okay. So anyway, the גמרא's Gemara current answer is we said
any animal that chews its cud doesn't have teeth and it's טהור.
tahor. Now we're sort of saying no, no, no,
implicitly what the גמרא Gemara is saying is any animal that doesn't
chew its cud and doesn't have front teeth is kosher. But a
cow, so presume he's saying you don't need to know that. But
a camel that chews its cud because it does have those teeth
is not kosher. So rather than saying chewing its cud tells you
about teeth, it sounds like we're shifting out to making a claim
that there are two criteria. Chewing cud, forget about the hooves, if
it also has no teeth, it's kosher. So let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes with this. So the גמרא Gemara says והרי בן
גמל, Vaharei ben gamal, how about a young camel? דניבי נמי לית
ליה, denivi nami leit leh, that does not yet have those incisors,
those teeth, and we know that a young camel's also not kosher.
So you can't just judge based on teeth. ותירוץ, Vetirutz, so that's
asking assuming that it was two criteria. Chew cud plus no teeth.
But now let's go back to the original way we, this statement
sounded. והרי שפן וארנבת, Vaharei shafan ve'arnevet, how about these other non-kosher
animals that chew cuds and don't have split hooves? Like the hyrax
and the rabbit or whatever they are. דמעלת גרה הן, demalat gerah
hen, they chew their cud, actually it will be a problem because
apparently rabbits and the whatever hyrax don't really chew their cud, they're
not ruminants. They do some type of chewing or whatever, but okay,
that's an interesting thing in defining what chewing its cud means.
ויש להם שיניים למעלה וטמאין. veyesh lahem shinayim lema'lah utme'in. Now that's
exactly what we just said by a camel. They chew its cud,
it has teeth, and they're טמא. tamei. So at one point the
גמרא Gemara was saying that the statement means two criteria. Chew cud
and no teeth is טהור. tahor. So then it's okay, chew cud
with teeth is טמא, tamei, that's a camel. But now it's saying
your statement really sounded like it meant if it chews its cud,
it doesn't have teeth. So the same way we had a contrary
evidence by a camel, we now also have contrary evidence by all
these things, right, by the hyrax and by the rabbit and whatever,
that these things chew their cud and do have teeth and you
were saying anything that chews its cud doesn't have teeth. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואטו שיניים מכתיבי באורייתא, Va'atu shinayim mikhtivei be'ora'ita,
why are you bringing a קשיא kushya about teeth? The Torah doesn't
talk about teeth. What do I care about teeth? Okay. אלא הכי
קאמר, Ella hakhi ka'amar, this is what the statement really meant.
It doesn't mean chewing its cud will tell you about teeth. Some
animals chew its cud have, some animals chew its cud don't. Okay,
here's what it means. It means the opposite. כל בהמה שאין לה
שיניים למעלה, Kol behemah she'ein lah shinayim lema'lah, it doesn't mean chewing
its cud will tell you about teeth. It means the opposite. Any
animal that doesn't have teeth above, בידוע שהיא מעלת גרה ומפרסת פרסה,
beyadu'a shehi ma'alat gerah umafriset parsah, actually you have a shortcut to
the סימנים Simanim of the Torah and here's your shortcut. If it
has no upper teeth, you know it is a ruminant with split
hooves. So that actually is sufficient way of telling that you have
a kosher animal is you look at the upper teeth. And now
we've dealt with the problem because all of the other non-kosher animals
like the hyrax and the rabbit and the camel, we said have
teeth above. So what we're not saying is: it's not chewing cud
tells you about teeth; it's the opposite: teeth tells you about the
chewing cud. And if it doesn't have teeth, you know it chews
its cud, and you know it has split hooves. So what about
the בן גמל? ben gamal? The only problem is the young camel.
So that is the only exception. So let's take a look at
the גירסא, girsa, because, yeah exactly. Are you saying it was like
imprecisely said?
Because the גירסא, girsa, just like we said, גמל גמל.
gamal gamal. I know, I know he is switching it. He is
saying it was imprecise, correct. Okay, or not necessarily switching, but saying
it was imprecise. So it says ומפרסת
וטהורה. u'mafreses v'tahora. So the גמרא Gemara says וליבדוק בפרסותיו, v'livdok b'parsosav,
so who needs new סימנים? simanim? Just look at the hooves.
So the גמרא Gemara says כגון שהיו, k'gon shehayu, I mean, כגון
שהיו פרסותיו חתוכות. k'gon shehayu parsosav hatuchos.
Let's say there was an animal brought to you that its hooves
were cut off and you wanted, and you wanted to know if
it was כשר kosher or not, you had another way of checking.
You could check by the teeth. וכדברי רב חסדא, u'ch'divrei Rav Chisda,
like רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, דאמר רב חסדא, d'amar Rav Chisda,
היה מהלך במדבר, hayah mehalech b'midbar,
you were going in the wilderness, ומצא בהמה שפרסותיו חתוכות. u'matza behemah
sheparsosav hatuchos.
And you had nothing to eat, and you found this animal, which
is a species which is totally unfamiliar with to you, and the
hooves were cut off. So you had no way of knowing and
it was the only animal, you were there in the wilderness, it
was one animal that you found. So and you wanted to know
if it was a כשר kosher species or not. Okay, בודק בפיו,
bodek b'piv, and now maybe you could, so even if you waited
to see if it chews its cud, it wouldn't tell you if
it had split hooves or not. So now comes into use the
other test. בודק בפיו, bodek b'piv, check its mouth, אם אין לו
שיניים למעלה, im ein lo shinayim l'maalah, if it has no upper
teeth, בידוע שהיא טהורה, biyaduah shehi tehorah, then you know that it
is a כשר kosher animal, that it is a ruminant that has
split hooves, אם לאו, im lav, and without those upper teeth, בידוע
שהיא טמאה, biyaduah shehi temei'ah, it is a non-כשר kosher animal. ובלבד,
u'vilvad, but
there is one exception, which we said, which was the young camel.
ובלבד שיכיר גמל, u'vilvad sheyakir gamal, as long as you recognize a
camel and know it is not a camel. So the גמרא Gemara
said, גמל, gamal, a camel, ניבי אית ליה, nivei is lei, we
just said that it does have these big front teeth. So that
is not a problem, that is not an exception. אלא ובלבד שיכיר
בן גמל. ella u'vilvad sheyakir ben gamal. No, we mean that you
have to recognize a young camel. So if you have no idea
what it is, then we're telling a principle that an animal without
front teeth, upper front teeth, actually is a ruminant that has split
hooves and you can eat it with the one exception of a
young camel, and if you know it is not a young camel
then you can trust this סימן. siman. Now I do not
know, well, anyway why would you need to go by this today?
We can know what things are ruminants and split hooves, we're not
walking the desert without knowing what animals are. But anyway, but the
other interesting thing, besides what do we go by it, I think
it is the question about whether it actually scientifically bears out is,
I don't know, I'm sure somebody has checked into this to see
whether this really is true or, about to get to another statement
in the גמרא Gemara as well about רוב, rov, that only one
case fits this case and again from what I understand,
that actually these are not
necessarily accurate. I was actually just recently on a little tour of
the Bronx Zoo with Rabbi Natan Slifkin, took my kids on it.
And he said, anyway, and he said that yeah, that the statements
the גמרא Gemara makes, for example the תורה Torah lists animals that
are ruminants and don't have split hooves, the camel, the hyrax, whatever,
so the גמרא Gemara as we're about to say is going to
say those are the only animals that are ruminants without split hooves.
But the תורה Torah never says that. The תורה Torah just gives
some examples and actually the problem is that they are not the
only animals that are that way. So anyway the גמרא Gemara here
is making a statement that the only animals without teeth, which isn't
even mentioned in the תורה, Torah, that is a problem is the
younger camel. Let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, how can you say
that you only exclude the young camel? לאו אמרת דאיכא בן גמל,
lav amart d'ika ben gamal, once you admit that there is an
exception, that there is a young camel, so איכא נמי מינא אחרינא
דדמי לבן גמל. ika nami mina achrina d'dami l'ben gamal. Why aren't
we concerned that there are other things that are like a young
camel that are an exception to the rule, that don't have front
teeth and are still not kosher, top teeth. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka daiteich, so that doesn't make sense
that there are other exceptions. דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל, d'tani d'vei Rabbi
Yishmael, we taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, ואת
הגמל כי מעלה גרה הוא, v'es hagamal ki maaleh gerah hu, and
don't eat the camel because it, הוא, hu, it is a, is
a something that the, you know that although it chews its cud
does not have split hooves. So it says, so here is the
comment. שליט בעולמו, shalit b'olamo, the master of his world, God, יודע
yodeia knows שאין לך דבר שמעלה גרה וטמא אלא גמל, she'ein l'cha
davar shemaaleh gerah v'tamei ella gamal, that the only thing that chews
its cud that is not kosher is the camel, meaning the camel
and the other things mentioned there in the תורה, Torah, the camel
and the rabbit and the hyrax and so on. Those are the
only things that chew their cuds that don't have split hooves. Okay,
לפיכך פירש בו הכתוב הוא. l'fikach pirash bo hakasuv hu. Therefore the
תורה Torah said it, these are the things that are problem there's
nothing else in the world you have to worry about. Now by
the case by the way of the pig, I believe it is
true. Pig is the only animal with split hooves that does not
chew its cud. Okay, but the reverse is not the truth, there
are more, there are animals that chew cuds that don't have split
hooves that are not mentioned in the תורה, Torah, but רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael is saying not that way, only these. And therefore since
it is only these, you don't have to worry, the only thing
you have to worry about the... one exception from among these animals.
And the one exception from among these animals about the teeth is
the young camel. So if you know it's not a young camel,
since that was the only one exception and we only limited to
these few animals that are a problem, then without the top teeth
you know that it is not a problematic animal, you know it's
kosher.
It's probably the only animal in the area they're familiar with.
Right, that could be, it could be the only animal in like
the Middle East or something that has these issues. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר רב חסדא, V'amar Rav Chisda,
so now that we're on this topic about other ways of detecting
סימנים simanim that are not in the תורה, Torah, האי מהלך בדרך
ומצא בהמה שפיה גמום. hai mehalech b'derech u'matza behema she'piha gamum. You
were going in the desert and you found an animal that its
mouth was cut, meaning basically like you couldn't check the front teeth.
Oh, so you can't check, like somehow the jaw came off or
whatever, you can't check the front teeth. Okay, so now what are
you going to do? So now בדיק בפרסותיה. badik b'parshoteha. So obviously
check the hooves, go to the תורה Torah סימן. siman. אם פרסותיה
סדוקות, im parshoteha s'dukot, if it has split hooves, בידוע שהיא טהורה,
biyadu'a she'hi tehora, it's kosher. Wait, what about the cud? You don't
have to check the cud? This is sufficient. But the problem is
that there's one exception, the pig. The pig is the only animal
with split hooves. So you have to know it's not a pig.
Exactly. Okay, אם לאו בידוע שהיא טמאה, im lav biyadu'a she'hi t'mea,
if not it's טמאה, t'mea, you have to assume
it's טמאה. t'mea. ובלבד שיכיר חזיר, ub'vilvad sheyakir chazir, as long as
you recognize the pig. לאו, lav, so the גמרא Gemara says because
the pig has split hooves and does not chew its cud.
What was the problem about the jaw if there's no jaws?
Oh, the lower jaw was actually, yeah, so actually the גמרא Gemara
said if you remember that the lower jaw is kosher, even if
it's missing the lower jaw. Anyway, it didn't say literally that the
whole jaw was removed. It just said somehow maybe the teeth were
cut out or something, right. But I just said the jaw was
removed. But actually it is kosher, the רמב"ם Rambam adds, the רמב"ם
Rambam adds
if the upper jaw is removed it's a טרפה, treifa, but there
was a serious debate about that because it wasn't on the official
list. Okay, so anyway, so here interestingly, right, the תורה Torah gives
two סימנים, simanim, but we are actually saying you can shortcut it
as long as you know the exceptions. Two סימנים simanim will tell
you definitely, but if you know the exception of the upper teeth,
then you can use that as a סימן. siman. If you know
the exception of the split hooves, the pig, you can use that
as a סימן. siman. So the גמרא Gemara says how do you
know pig is the only exception? The גמרא Gemara says one minute,
לאו אמרת דאיכא חזיר, lav amart de'ika chazir, you just admitted there's
a pig, איכא נמי מיני אחריני דדמי לחזיר, ika nami minei achrinei
d'dami l'chazir, there are other things like a pig, and maybe we
have to worry about them. לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka da'atach, that
doesn't make sense, דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל, d'tanya d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, ואת
החזיר כי מפריס פרסה הוא. v'et hachazir ki mafris parsa hu.
As far as the pig, it has split hooves but does not
chew its cud. שליט בעולמו, Shalit b'olamo, the Master of the Universe,
יודע שאין לך דבר שמפריס פרסה וטמא אלא חזיר. yode'a she'ein lecha
davar she'mafris parsa v'tamei ela chazir. לפיכך פרטה הכתוב, l'fichach partah hakatuv,
therefore
it said this. This is the one thing with split hooves that
does not chew its cud, but there's nothing else, so as long
as you know it has split hooves and it's not a pig,
you're okay. ואמר רב חסדא, V'amar Rav Chisda, and רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says: האי מהלך במדבר, hai mehalech bamidbar,
once again, going in the wilderness, ומצא בהמה שפיה גמום ופרסותיה חתוכות.
u'matza behema she'piha gamum u'parshoteha chatuchot.
You can't use either of these shortcuts, right?
Its teeth are cut out and or whatever its jaw somehow is
removed or the gums and its hooves are cut off. So you
have no shortcuts. Okay, what are you going to do?
So בדיק בבשרא, badik bivshara, check its
flesh. אם מהלך שתי וערב, im mehalech sheti va'erev, you know
when they tell you like when you're cutting meat they say cut
it against the grain like the meat goes in one direction. So
if there's sections of meat that go one way and sections that
go another way, it goes in both directions, בידוע שהיא טהורה, biyadu'a
she'hi tehora, it's kosher.
So presumably if you look at the musculature of these animals, one
of these things had a picture, you know some of it runs
in one direction and some of it runs in the other direction.
No, there wasn't a picture here, there was a picture I think
in the back.
Oh, if the muscles like in humans, right, the muscles sort of
go in multiple directions. So apparently that means that the meat it
can be cut in multiple directions. Okay, שהיא טהורה, she'hi tehora, בידוע
שהיא טמאה. biyadu'a she'hi t'mea. Otherwise it's not kosher. ובלבד שיכיר ערוד,
ub'vilvad sheyakir arod, as long as you know the wild donkey which
is apparently an exception. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, לאו
איכא ערוד, lav ika arod, once you're admitting there's a wild donkey,
איכא נמי מיני אחריני דדמי לערוד, ika nami minei achrinei d'dami l'arod,
there are other things that might be an exception and here you
can't quote a פסוק pasuk because this whole thing about the way
in which the meat, direction of the meat is not in the
תורה. Torah. So the גמרא Gemara says no, גמירי, gemiri, we have
a tradition about this, דליכא, d'leka, that the only animal that's an
exception to this rule is the wild donkey. And that is true,
I have no idea. והיכא בדיק, veheicha badik, where do you check
for this issue of the direction of the meat? אמר אביי בתומא
דרב חסדא, amar Abaye b'tuma d'Rav Chisda, בקמצי דאוקץ, b'kamchei d'ukatz, אביי
Abaye says according to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, by the sort of
thighs, by the by the rear, so you know as you saw
in that picture, towards the back, towards the flanks, the rear flanks
of the animal. Okay, so that is interesting. cut about other ways
of determining but also with assertions that the תורה's Torah examples are
the only examples of things that fall in those categories which again
from what I understand is true about the pig but not about
the other animals. Yes.
The definition of a species is not the same as the scientific
definition. There are about ten species of pigs and about sixty species
of camels.
Right. Okay. Correct. Okay. Okay, that is correct. All right, now סימני
חיה. simanei chayah. Now the משנה mishnah said those are the סימנים
simanim for בהמה behemah and חיה. chayah. Okay, so now that we're
going to discuss the חיה chayah issue. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan we
taught, אלו הן סימני חיה, elu hen simanei chayah, these are the
characteristics of a חיה chayah of a non-domesticated species. So the גמרא
Gemara says חיה בכלל בהמה היא לסימנין, chayah bekhlal behemah hi lesimanim,
who needs other characteristics? Right, they're all lumped together when it comes
to issues about mammals, right, we say split hooves, chew their cud.
We don't have different indicators for wild species and non-wild species.
So the גמרא Gemara says you're right, we're not talking about כשרות
kashrus anymore. We're talking about there's another reason why we're talking about
distinguishing
חיה chayah from בהמה. behemah. Because a חיה chayah when you שחט
shacht a חיה chayah you have to cover its blood and the
fat is permissible. So you want to know if something is a
חיה chayah or a בהמה. behemah. So we're not talking about כשרות,
kashrus, we're talking about distinguishing חיה chayah from בהמה behemah להתיר חלבה.
lehattir chelvah. You want to say that the חלב, chelev, the fat
is permissible and that's only true if it's a חיה chayah not
a בהמה. behemah. והכי קאמר vehachi ka'amar and here's what it says:
אלו הן סימני חיה שחלבה מותר. elu hen simanei chayah shechelvah muttar.
The following are the characteristics of a חיה chayah to distinguish it
from a בהמה behemah to tell you that its fat is permissible.
כל שיש לה קרנים וטלפים, kol sheyesh lah karnayim utlafiym,
anything that has
horns and hooves.
Okay, רבי דוסא אומר יש לה קרנים אי אתה צריך לחזור על
הטלפים. Rabbi Dosa omer yesh lah karnayim i attah tzarikh lachzor al
hatlafiym. If it has horns you don't have to worry about the
hooves. יש לה טלפים צריך אתה לחזור לקרנים. yesh lah tlafiym tzarikh
attah lachzor lekarnayim. If it has hooves you have to worry about
the horns. So it's basically for him about the horns. Now what
is the
focus in the גמרא Gemara is going to be about the horns.
What is the issue? Yeah, we're going to look at all those
pictures in a minute. What is the issue about the hooves? So
it sounds like from רש״י Rashi basically the hooves fall by the
wayside anyway because of רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa and maybe they really
weren't set to or at if they're set to exclude anything they're
set to exclude not just to distinguish between a חיה chayah and
a בהמה behemah but also to distinguish between non-כשר kosher חיות chayot
like wild animals that don't have hooves at all like bears or
something. I don't know, is there any animal that doesn't have hooves
that has horns? I can't think of one offhand.
Some South American camel.
Don't have hooves?
Well they don't have the kind of hooves. Well I don't know,
they have rhinoceros, wait a minute.
Rhinoceros would be a good example. Rhinoceros, of course. Okay, there you
go.
All right, so they have horns.
Yes, they have horns. No, they have paws. They're like not right.
Okay, so one explanation of why we're mentioning hooves here is to
not distinguish חיה chayah and בהמה behemah but to distinguish between non-כשר
kosher חיות. chayot. So it would have to have hooves to be
a כשר kosher חיה chayah and it would have to have horns
to be a חיה chayah not a בהמה. behemah. That's one approach.
The other approach is if you look at this lovely picture, רבנו
תם Rabbeinu Tam but he says here hooves does not mean any
hooves. It means hooves that are characteristic of a חיה. chayah. This
is a cow's hoof and this is a deer's hoof. Very different,
right? Long and thin is the חיה chayah as opposed to sort
of short and stubby is the cow. So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
says the criteria here to distinguish חיה chayah and בהמה behemah which
is our emphasis
is חיה chayah type of hooves is what it means. So you
can look at the hoof and you can have to look at
the horns and then רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa says no, it's enough
just to look at the horn. So now let's take a look
at, again we're not worrying about non-כשר. kosher. Within the world of
כשר kosher animals, chews cud, whatever, how do you know חיה chayah
or בהמה? behemah? So it's hoof and horn? Right, is it hooves
and horns or is it just horns?
Do female animals have horns?
I don't know,
but some don't.
I think that's the only one. I think right.
No, but it would mean that the species. Right, but it means
the species. It doesn't mean this particular example. Right, we're not dealing
with going in the wilderness anymore, we're talking about identifying the species.
Okay, so now the question is what do you mean horns? I
mean if you say you need both horns and hooves and the
hooves are distinctive, fine, but if just horns, we know כשר kosher
animals have horns, rams and bulls etc. So now we're going to
say according to רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa the focus is on horns.
What are the distinctive horns? So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
So it means certain kinds of horns.
Right. בקרש bekeresh when it comes to the כרש, keresh, אע״פ שאין
לו אלא קרן אחת af al pi she'ein lo ela keren achat
although it has only one horn, מותר, muttar, permissible. What's the כרש?
keresh? What the heck is a כרש? keresh? Good question. Yes, it's
the famed unicorn. You know, everybody has these speculations because we don't
know of any animal that has one horn, you know, that so
what's his name, the שיחת חולין Sichat Chullin tries to suggest that
it is the giraffe. Now you'll tell me you've never seen a
horn on a giraffe, but a giraffe does have like two. It
has these things, but they have a picture in here, it has
like a bump coming out in the center. So
it's right. So that's what. with
ostriches, Scott? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're
going to look at the horns. וכללו, Vechalalu, is that really true,
that a horn is sufficient to tell you that it's a חיה?
chayah? דהרי עז, Deharei ez, how about a goat, right? דיש לו
קרניים, Deyesh lo karnayim, it has horns,
וטלפים. utlafim. Now, hoofs, does not have חיה-like chayah hoofs, so this
really just means, so maybe וטלפים utlafim here is לאו דוקא. lav
davka. The emphasis on this whole discussion is going to be about
the horns, so let's just ignore the hoofs for now. Maybe it's
going according to רבי דוסא. Rebbi Dosa. So anyway, you have a
ram, excuse me, a goat, right, a goat, that it has horns,
וחלבן אסור, vechelban assur, and its fat is forbidden, it's a בהמה.
behemah. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כרוכות בעינן, keruchot bainan, it's
not enough
that you have horns, they have to be bundled. What does bundled
mean? Here is a picture
of a goat's horns, and you see they're sort of like knots,
and they're like this nice horn-like shofar-like shape. Okay, this is a
picture of a horn that is not notched, and they sort of
grow, almost it looks like a sort of like a tree, what's
it called, the inside of a tree there, they sort of grow
bundled, like one layered on top of the other as it continues
to grow out. Okay, so apparently the גמרא Gemara says that's what
the horn of a חיה chayah looks like, not this.
What? Ridged.
Yeah, like
ridged, ridged, ridged.
You see all those ridges? Okay, which that would be a חיה,
chayah, has
the ridges.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying, well the problem is that this
is certainly not true for all חיות, chayos, and it's even true
for some בהמות. behemos.
So what is the answer so far?
כרוכות, keruchot, that the horn that defines a חיה chayah is this
type of thing which is like bundled, meaning it's one thing layered
on top of the other, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, דהרי שור דכרוכות וחלבן אסור, deharei shor dekeruchot vechelban assur, that's
not going to work, an ox's horns are exactly that, they grow
layered one on top, the layers grow one on top of the
other, and that is a בהמה, behemah, not a חיה. chayah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, חרוקות בעינן, charukot bainan, fine, so back
to this, we need ridged, ridged, that's like the ones I showed
you, so we need ridged horns, that's the problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, we're back to the problem about the goat.
דהרי עז דחרוקות וחלבן אסור, deharei ez decharukot vechelban assur, we have
a goat that has ridged horns and its fat is forbidden. מפוצלות
בעינן, mefutzalot bainan, so we need branched. If you think about a
deer's horns, right, here, I'll use this picture, right, antlers, that's a
good point, that's why I guess they're called antlers, right? So you
have moose and deer, whatever, right, so these things are more like
branched type of horns than pointed. Okay, well that works for a
moose which is a חיה, chayah, right, but it does not, and
it works for a deer, so so far we seem to be...
what? Moose is kosher? Yeah, why not? Absolutely. Okay. Never heard of
it. Hunters will often and it'll feed you for a year, it's
huge. Okay, never heard of it even served at those crazy kosher
dinners. You got to do one of those. All right. So branched,
branched is a חיה chayah is what we're saying. Branched horns makes
it a חיה. chayah. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והרי,
veha'rei, so that's true, so branched
is going to
be חיה chayah not בהמה, behemah, but we have an exception on
the other side. והרי צבי דאין מפוצלות וחלבן מותר, veha'rei tzvi de'ein
mefutzalot vechelban muttar, when it comes to a deer, it's not branched,
and it is a חיה. chayah. Now what do you mean a
deer is not branched? Isn't the classic deer branched? So רש״י Rashi
says, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says the following:
והרי צבי דאין מפוצלות.
veha'rei
tzvi de'ein mefutzalot.
It's eight lines down in the narrow lines.
So says רש״י: Rashi:
לא ידענא מאי קאמר דאבדי מפוצלות הן, lo yadana mai ka'amar d'avadei
mefutzalot hein, deer's horns are branched. So רש״י Rashi says: ונראה בעיני
שמה שאנו קורים צבי לא היו הם
קורים צבי אלא אותם הנקראים שטיינבוק,
venir'eh be'einai shemah she'anu korim tzvi lo hayu
heim
korim tzvi ela otam hanikra'im Steinbuck, וקרניים שלהם אינן מפוצלות. vekarnayim shelahem
einan mefutzalot. So a Steinbuck is an ibex... no that's a wild
goat. I think it's some kind of animal. It's a South African
animal. It's a South African antelope. Yeah. What? How would רש״י Rashi
know about that? רש״י Rashi is in northern... I think they were
14 in South... Okay. So anyway, yeah, so here רש״י Rashi says
here, this is, I guess it's this picture too here, okay, which
it's a wild goat, okay, so there it's ridged, it's not branched,
and it's a חיה. chayah. Now the author of the book שיחת
חולין Sichat Chullin points out very nicely that deers in the Middle
East and in Israel have non-branched antlers. So it's not, it doesn't
have to be רש״י Rashi's Steinbuck which is a type of a
goat. It could very well be a deer. but a deer, a
Middle Eastern deer fits this definition. It does not have, it's not
branched. So the גמרא Gemara says you cannot say that branched is
necessary, we have types of deer that are not branched and that
are a חיה. chayah. So the גמרא Gemara says חדורות בעינן. chadurot
beinan. Okay, so now we need them to be חדורות. chadurot. What
does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says either it means perfectly circular
at the base and that the horns of בהמות behemos are more
like, you know, are not perfectly circular, they're less, they're more irregular,
or it might mean that it comes up to a very thin
point at the top, which you can certainly see in some of
these cases. I mean look how pointy right the tops of these
are as opposed to, I don't know if it has pictures of
the other animals. And deers particularly pointedly, yeah, he does. I have
to, yeah I have to bring the pictures in. Okay, anyway, so
presumably, yeah, so it has to be a very thin point at
the top. Yeah, here's examples, right? You see pointing to the little
pointy tops of the antlers. So it has to be a pointy
top. That is a type of a horn that makes something a
חיה chayah and not a בהמה. behemah. הילכך, hilkach, therefore says the
גמרא, Gemara, היכא דמפצלא, heicha demiftzala, if it actually is branched, לא
דינא ולא דיינא, lo dina velo dayana, there's no rule and there's
no judge, meaning it's just, there's no question at all that it
is a חיה chayah and not a בהמה. behemah. What about the
need of חדורות? chadurot? No, no, חדורות chadurot was because there are
some things that are not branched and they're still okay, right? That
are, like the deer. Okay, but anything that is branched is certainly
a חיה, chayah, end of discussion. Okay, so branched is sufficient to
tell you it's a חיה. chayah. היכא דלא מפצלא, heicha delo miftzala,
if it's not branched and we know there are some things that
are still a חיה chayah like this deer, then בעינן כרוכות חדורות
וחרוקות. beinan keruchot chadurot vecharukot. You need all three of the previous
criteria because, you know, some work for some and some not the
other. You need it to be layered, you need it to come
to a point, and you need it to be ridged. והוא דמיבלע
חירקייהו, vehu demivla chirkayhu, and but the ridge is only when the
ridges are like overlapping ridges. Like if you look at some of
these things, right, you see how close the ridges are, you know,
they're like extremely, one on top of the other. So ridges are
only good if they're very overlapping. והיינו ספיקא דעיזא דכרכוס, vehaynu sefeika
deiza dekarchos, and this is the doubt relating to the goats of
Karchos. These goats were questioned whether they were wild goats or not
wild goats, were they חיה chayah or בהמה? behemah? And presumably, their
horns had these ridges but were they really overlapping enough to be
considered a good enough of a סימן siman that this was a
חיה? chayah? So this was the issue about these goats. ההיא עיזא
דכרכוס, hahi iza dekarchos, there were these goats of Karchos דהוי בי
ריש גלותא, dehavi be reish galuta, which was in the house of
the Reish Galuta, דעקר מלא צנא דתרבא מינה, deakar malei tzana detarba
minei, they removed a huge basketful of fat from it. Okay, meaning
it had a ton of חלב chelev and they wanted to eat
the חלב, chelev, they want to know if it was a חיה.
chayah. Now we just got through saying that it's, you know, it's
not branched, so that's not sufficient. It has these other סימנים, simanim,
but with the ridges, were the ridges might not have been sufficiently
overlapped. So is it kosher or not? I mean is it a
חיה chayah or not, and can you eat the fat? רב אחא
אסר, Rav Acha asar, Rav Acha said it was forbidden. ושמואל בריה
דרבי אבהו אכל מיניה, uShmuel breih deRabbi Abbahu achal minei, and Shmuel
the son of Rabbi Abbahu said it's kosher and once again to
prove his point he ate some of the fat. That it's a
חיה chayah and he ate some of the fat. קרי אנפשיה, kari
anafshei, and he said about himself, מפרי פי איש תשבע בטנו, mipri
pi ish tisba bitno, from the fruit of your labor your stomach
will be filled and from the fruit of your mouth. Meaning, so
here because of my פסק, psak, I was able to get some
of the fat. So it's quite interesting again, they're not concerned about
a concern of נוגע בדבר, nogeia bedavar, they're more actually doing this
to show, look, I really פסק pasken it's permitted, I'm willing to
eat from it. שלחו מהתם, shalechu mehatam, so they sent from ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל בריה דרבי אבהו, hilchata kevasei deShmuel
breih deRabbi Abbahu, the halacha is like Shmuel the son of Rabbi
Abbahu that this goat of Karchos is a חיה chayah and the
fat is permissible. But nevertheless, והיזהרו ברבינו אחא, vehizaharu beRabbeinu Acha, show
respect to Rabbeinu Acha's position, don't flagrantly rule against him and certainly
not in his presence. שמאיר עיני גולה הוא, shemeir einei golah hu,
he is the light, he gives light to the eyes of the
diaspora.
So he's a great personage, so you should not, you know, flagrantly
rule against him even though the הלכה halacha really is against him.
That phrase of course מאיר עיני הגולה, meir einei hagolah, right, give
כבוד. kavod. We're back to that. Exactly. Exactly. And that phrase, I
know, מאיר עיני הגולה, meir einei hagolah, right, is a phrase that
was used, you might know, with the מהר"ם מרוטנבורג, Maharam miRottenburg, that
was a phrase that rarely reappeared. There were other phrases that reappeared,
but the one time that in particular was the מהר"ם Maharam was
said, you know, he's, you know, was the מאיר פני הגולה. meir
pnei hagolah. Okay, we will end here.